Theodore W. Torrey papers, 1945-1986 C7
Indiana University Archives
Theodore W. Torrey papers
1945-1986
Indiana University Archives
Torrey, Theodore W. (Theodore Willett), 1907-1986
C7
.4 cubic feet
Theodore W. Torrey, 1907-1986, was a Professor in the Zoology Department at Indiana University from 1932 until his retirement in 1972. The Theodore W. Torrey papers, comprising .4 cubic feet and spanning 1945 to 1986, consists largely unpublished manuscripts, most likely prepared for talks given at the Sunday Evening Discussion Group. Also included are several speeches, two copies of one of his publications and 2 personal items.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Theodore W. Torrey was born in Woodbine, Iowa in 1907 and spent his early years in Colorado. In 1927, he graduated from the University of Denver and subsequently received his M.A. (1929) and Ph.D. (1932) from Harvard University. Torrey was a Professor in the Zoology Department at Indiana University from 1932 until his retirement in 1972. Torrey was Chairman of the Department of Zoology from 1948 to 1966.
Professor Torrey taught courses in embryology and comparative anatomy for pre-medical students and advanced courses in experimental embryology for seniors and graduate students. He developed and taught a course in developmental anatomy. The focus of his research was on the investigation of vertebrate evolution, primarily the excretory and reproductive organs. In his teaching he was one of the pioneers for using three-dimensional photographs and visual aids in both lectures and the laboratory. His textbook, Morphogenesis of the Vertebrates went through four editions from 1962-1979. Torrey died on August 31, 1986.
Arrangement
The Theodore W. Torrey papers are organized into four series: Professional materials, Sunday Evening Discussion Group materials, Speaking engagements, and Personal materials.
Scope and Content Note
The Theodore W. Torrey Papers, 1945-1986, are organized in four series: Professional Materials, Sunday Evening Discussion Group, Speaking Engagements, and Personal Materials. With the exception of the items in Professional Materials, all items were forwarded to the Archives by Biology Professor L.S. McClung in 1983 and 1984.
The Professional Materials consist of two copies of one of his publications and an item from his course in Developmental Anatomy which correlates references in the lab manual to the 2nd and 3rd editions of his textbook and which was probably meant as a handout to students in the class.
The Sunday Evening Discussion Group Materials contain typewritten and handwritten copies of talks Torrey prepared, most probably, according to Professor McClung, for the Sunday Evening Discussion Group, a faculty group which included President Wells and which met in rotation at the members' homes for paper presentations and discussion. The Discussion Group materials, most of which are undated, are arranged by title. Although most of the items are undated, citations and references in a few of the texts give approximate dates of their creation.
Speaking Engagements Materials consist of typed and handwritten copies of speeches he gave and are arranged chronologically.
In Personal Materials are two items: a "Petition" presented to Torrey when he stepped down as chair of the department and "The Torrey Genesis," a genealogy he wrote.
Acquisition Information
Gift; L.S. McClung, 1983-1984; Accession 94/015.
Provenance
Deposited in the Archives in 1983 and 1984 by Professor L. S. McClung who received them from Professor Torrey with directions to deposit them in the Archives.
Zoologists --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Zoology teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Sunday Evening Discussion Group (Indiana University); Indiana University -- Faculty -- Intellectual life -- 20th century; Torrey, Theodore W. (Theodore Willett), 1907-1986 -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington -- Faculty -- Intellectual life -- 20th century
- Professional materials, 1949; 1971
  - Torrey, Theodore W. (Box 1)
    - "Zoology and Its Makers at Indiana University." Bios 20, no. 2: 67-99., (May 1949) (Box 1)
    - "Zoology and Its Makers at Indiana University: Sequel", July 1968 (Box 1)
  - "Zoology and Its Makers at Indiana University." Reprinted from Bios 20, no. 2: 67-99., (May 1949) (Box 1)
  - "Z-215--Developmental Anatomy.", 1971? (Box 1)
    General
    Typewritten.
- Sunday Evening Discussion Group materials, Undated
  - "Anthony van Leeuwenhoek.", Undated (Box 1)
  - "The Architecture of the Filterable Viruses.", Undated. (Box 1)
    Handwritten.
  - "The Coincident Discovery of Ideas.", Undated. (Box 1)
  - "Congenital Malformations in Man.", 1963? (Box 1)
    Typewritten. Handwritten notes attached. Citation in text is dated 1963.
  - "C. O. Whitman and the Early History of American Zoology.", Undated. (Box 1)
  - "Darwinian Evolution.", 1956? (Box 1)
    Handwritten. Citation to Scientific American, 1956.
  - "The Functional Nervous System.", Undated. (Box 1)
  - "History of the Microscope.", Undated. (Box 1)
  - "The Neurone as a Trophic Unit.", Undated. (Box 1)
  - "The Problem of a Liberal Education." Presented to the Discussion Group, Sunday, March 11, 1945. (Box 1)
  - "The Problem of Animal Development.", Undated. (Box 1)
    Opens with a reference to the war. Handwritten.
  - "The Scars of Human Evolution.", Undated. (Box 1)
    Handwritten. Attached is an undated article from an unidentified periodical: "The Scars of Human Evolution" by Wilton M. Krogman.
  - "Sex Determination.", Undated. (Box 1)
  - "Sex Differentiation in the Vertebrates.", Undated. (Box 1)
  - "What is Life?", Undated. (Box 1)
  - "Zoology is the last.. .", Undated. (Box 1)
    Untitled. Typewritten.
- Speaking engagements, 1948-1961
  - "The Excretory Organs of Mammalian Embryos.", Undated (Box 1)
    Handwritten. Begins: "Members and guests of Sigma Xi."
  - "Presented at the Appreciation Dinner for Dr. Fernandus Payne.", 6 March 1948 (Box 1)
  - Eulogy for Dr. Alfred Kinsey., 27 August 1956 (Box 1)
  - "Payne Portrait Presentation.", 13 February 1961 (Box 1)
  - "Perspectives and Methods in Science.", 2 June 1961 (Box 1)
    Read at the Fifth Annual Indiana University Alumni Institute. Copy of the program attached.
- Personal materials, 1966; 1976
  - "A Petition.", 28 May 1966 (Box 1)
  - "The Torrey Genesis.", November 1976 (Box 1)